<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peaceable design being a modest account of the non-conformist's meetings : with some of their reasons for nonconformity, and the way of accomodation in the matter of religion, humbly proposed to publick consideration by some ministers of London against the sitting of Parliament in the year 1675.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08163934</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08163934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40985</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45150)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40985)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1231:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peaceable design being a modest account of the non-conformist's meetings : with some of their reasons for nonconformity, and the way of accomodation in the matter of religion, humbly proposed to publick consideration by some ministers of London against the sitting of Parliament in the year 1675.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8] (1st grouping)</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Humfrey--Cf. Halkett and Laing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40985:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40985:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Peaceable Deſign; BEING A MODEST ACCOUNT. OF THE Non-conformiſt's Meetings, With ſome of their Reaſons for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity: And the way of Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation in the matter of Religion.</p>
            <p>Humbly propoſed to publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration by ſome Miniſters of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> againſt the ſitting of Parliament in the Year 1675.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year MDCLXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40985:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40985:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WE humbly Judge our Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances have made it ſomething neceſſary to give the World a Taſt of ſome of thoſe many reaſons which have prevailed with us to be averſe to that conformity which we are called to by Law: Which had it ſprung from any Diſloyal or Rebellious Principles, could not have been conſiſtent with that inward Peace which we muſt judge our great concernment to be ſolicitous to maintain. We hope (ſave in the matters of our God) the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which are truly ours, will urge us to be ſubject unto Authority, and we do here profeſs that it is our full perſwaſion, that
<pb facs="tcp:40985:3"/>the <hi>Powers</hi> in being are of <hi>God,</hi> and that ſhould we do any thing derogatory to their due Honour, Rule, and Intereſt, it would be wickedneſs to be puniſh'd by the Judge, and introductive of our Eternal ruine and damnation. We are not unmindful of the high charges which are laid upon us to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King,</hi> and to be <hi>ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi> And God forbid that we ſhould ever deſire or deſign to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Tents of thoſe who are inclin'd or love to <hi>ſmite</hi> authority with either <hi>hand</hi> or <hi>tongue,</hi> or to ſupplant the Throne which God hath honoured, and guarded both by <hi>Laws,</hi> and providence. We cannot think the Sword well placed in <hi>Peters</hi> hands, nor that the Tongues or Hearts of any ſhould be inflamed with rage, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed with an arbitrary cenſoriouſneſs of Rulers actions, ſeeing we neither can, nor is it fit we ſhould ſtand upon equal ground with them. But we hope it cannot (and that it will not) be charged upon us as our crime, or as the production of inſolence, to tell the World wherein, and how we
<pb facs="tcp:40985:3"/>are diſtreſſed, nor to make our modeſt offers and propoſals, and humble ſupplications, as on the Knee unto our Rulers, in whoſe power God hath placed it to alleviate or remove our burthens, And it is their help and pity we earneſtly implore: Our perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are afflictive, and our burthens heavy on us: The reaſons of our Non-conformity we in part offer modeſtly to our Superiours, and as proſtrate Supplicants at their feet, we crave their conſideration of them: The Souls of Men are precious: Gods Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is our undoubted Intereſt and End: Our own Liberty to Preach Christ (not Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Treaſon or Rebellion) is dear, and would be grateful to us: And the Character of our Conſecration to God in the Goſpel of his dear Son engraven on us at our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, we take to be indelible. And we doubt not but that all who are acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Laws of Chriſt, will own his charge upon us to be indiſpenſible. If we be diſſatisfied about impoſed terms of this our Miniſterial Liberty, we crave the Reſolution of this weighty Caſe from our
<pb facs="tcp:40985:4"/>judicious, learned and ſerious Fathers and Brethren in the Service of the Goſpel. We hope we are not too obſtinate to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive convincing evidence and information from them, only when we have but named ſome things as we paſs, which are of more general notice, (ſuch as two of thoſe three Heads laid down <hi>p. 20, 21.</hi>) we deplore a diſquiſition or ſatisfaction candidly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their importance, and the Volumes of diſpute that have been writ, and might be pointed to by us for enlargement. We ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly promiſe them a quick and full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat from our miſtakes, and hearty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with them, when they offer what is truly fit to ſatisfie our doubts about matters in diſpute betwixt them and us. We have long born with patience many a ſmart reflection on us from both the Preſs and Pulpit, together with all the ſeverities to which we have been expoſed by vertue of thoſe Laws that have been made against us: And yet reſolve to uſe no other Weapons than Prayers and Tears, the antient Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of all afflicted Christians, nor ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:40985:4"/>our minds be (we truſt) at any time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated into illegal courſes, for our own relief; for ſuch unwarrantable and juſtly condemned Principles we diſown. And we hope our peaceable principles, tempers, and demeanors will not turn to our diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. We have here laid our Caſe and Reaſons a little open, together with ſome propoſals for a deſired accommodation for our joynt promotion of that Work which is profeſſed to be dear unto us all, that ſo the proſperity and strength of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> may be promoted by us all, without occaſions of, or inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to, thoſe mutual animoſities in the Church, which will become the ſport, and strength, and great advantage of forrein and domestick Enemies, and our great ſhame and diſadvantage here at home.</p>
            <p>As to the Materials of this ſhort Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, they have mostly been derived from a late Author, whoſe Spirit in all his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings hath breathed Peace at ſuch a rate,
<pb facs="tcp:40985:5"/>as that we think we may entitle him to the Character which St. <hi>Paul</hi> once fixed on <hi>Timothy,</hi> that he <hi>naturally careth</hi> for the Peace and Wellfare of the Church of Chriſt, and in that part eſpecially which God hath ſeated in theſe His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Dominions. We humbly depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate all Mens diſpleaſure, and crave the pardon of that excellent perſon, (whoſe Words and Actions ſeem weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and governed still by His tender Conſcience) that (two or three of us) have ſo boldly and freely uſed his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, without engaging his perſonal concernedneſs in the publication of theſe Sheets, wherein we do aſſure the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That he had no hand as to the Printing or Publication of them, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other uſe be made of him as to his Books and Papers. Reader, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what is here offered to thy peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and weigh the whole matter in an equal Ballance and pray with us that the intire intereſt of Holineſs, Truth, and Concord may be eſtabliſh'd, and promo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:40985:5"/>to Gods Glory, and the compleat fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity and ſecurity of His Majesty, and of the Church and State in theſe His Dominions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:40985:6"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 1. l 7. dele <hi>of</hi> 11. l. 14. add <hi>only,</hi> p. 2. l. 5. add <hi>our,</hi> p. 3. l. 24. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>that,</hi> p. 4. l. 11. add <hi>lay,</hi> l. 12. dele <hi>lay,</hi> p. 6. l. 6. add <hi>of,</hi> p. 9. l. 4. add <hi>Schoolmen.</hi> p. 12. l. 19. for <hi>contain</hi> r. <hi>contained,</hi> p. 16. l. 13. for <hi>and</hi> r. <hi>or,</hi> p. 26. l. ult. add <hi>booke,</hi> p. 30. l. 4. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>that,</hi> p. 32. l. 6. add <hi>againſt his perſon,</hi> p. 35. l. 3. for <hi>People</hi> r. <hi>Parliament,</hi> p. 46 l. 10. for <hi>Impurii</hi> r. <hi>Imperii,</hi> p. 46. l. 14. add <hi>ſtrong,</hi> p. 46. l. 20. for <hi>Impurii</hi> r. <hi>Imperii,</hi> p. 47. <hi>l.</hi> 16. for <hi>dinguiſh</hi> r. <hi>diſtinguiſh,</hi> p. 52. l. 18. for <hi>ſins</hi> r. <hi>lives,</hi> p. 53. l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. add <hi>be,</hi> p. 61. l. 21. for <hi>enfoying</hi> r. <hi>enjoyning,</hi> p. 65. l. 18. add <hi>not,</hi> l. 19. for <hi>caſe</hi> r. <hi>eaſe,</hi> p. 66. l. 14. for <hi>that</hi> r. <hi>as,</hi> l. 15. for <hi>as</hi> r. <hi>that,</hi> p. 67. l. 7. add <hi>Church,</hi> p. 76. l. 5. add <hi>ſhould be all, though they cut themſelves with Lances,</hi> p. 76. l. 9. for <hi>this</hi> r. <hi>things.</hi> p. 78. l. 1. add <hi>of Pride,</hi> p. 80. l. 9. for <hi>word</hi> r. <hi>work.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40985:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Peaceable Deſign:</head>
            <p>IT is the happineſs and birth-right of the People of this Nation, that if they lie under any grievance, they may have recourſe to the Parliament. There is no burden whereof we ought to be more ſenſible of than that which lies upon our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: We do humbly hope there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it will not be ill taken if we crave the liberty, to ſhew at leaſt what ails us; To make our apology for that wherein we ſeem to offend, and to offer ſomething for a general redreſs: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing a little collection out of ſome late papers (though ſeveral) of one perſon alone, will ſerve this triple oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40985:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>There are divers ſorts of Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, and they have their Meetings we know, not all on the ſame reaſons.</p>
            <p>There are ſome who have been, and are for Parochial Churches, who are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with their conſtitution, and if they might have freedom would ſtill chooſe them: And there are others that are in their Inclinations for the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational way only. For our parts who have put this Paper together, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our ſelves of the former ſort, and do here declare in the behalf of our ſelves and others of our Brethren, that we do not go from the Pariſh Church in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to it, as if ſuch Congregations were no Churches, being very deeply ſenſible when our Lord hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Tares ſhould not be plucked up for fear of endangering even but <hi>ſome of the Wheat,</hi> what a grievous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure it may like to be to him, if we ſhould go to root up <hi>all the Wheat</hi> for fear of the Tares, which to Un-church whole Pariſhes, were to do: Nor is it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40985:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of affectation, pride, vanity, oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, faction, or ſelf-advantage that we do it, we could not anſwer ſuch a charge againſt us, if we did ſo.</p>
            <p>Two things therefore we will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that our Pariſh-churhes are true Churches: And that it is our duty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to deſire and endeavour their union and proſperity. And what would any Conformiſt have of us more, unleſs it be alſo to joyn with them there in the participation of the Ordinances, which ſome of us refuſe not neither, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient occaſion. Well, upon what ground then ſhall we offer our apology for the cauſe we undertake? why we will give it impartially. As we grant thoſe two things to be our duty, ſo muſt we aſſume that which will not, and can not be denyed us, that it is the duty likewiſe of thoſe who are ſet apart to the offiice of the Miniſtry (ſuppoſing them every way to be ſit &amp; called) to preach the Goſpel by way of diſcharge of the office. We have the Apoſtles expreſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40985:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>authority and example for this, who when they were threatned, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſpeak no more in Chriſt's name, have left us their anſwer on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, <hi>We ought to obey God rather than Man.</hi> We have the precedent alſo of the firſt three hundred years after theſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles when the Goſpel was never preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but contrary to the will of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, that is, againſt the Laws and Edicts of the Emperors: Now we muſt down this rule, that when two duties lay come together, ſo that we cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the one but we muſt omit the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the greater duty muſt take place of the leſs. The rule apears in its own light, and alſo from Scripture, <hi>I will have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and not Sacrifice.</hi> What is the meaning, but that when acts of righteouſneſs and mercy fall in, ſuch du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as that of ſacrifice, which are leſs, muſt give way. Here then is our caſe plainly, which of theſe is the greater duty? We are to ſeek Unity, and to preach the Goſpel. If we keep our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Churches,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40985:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>we muſt not preach the Goſpel, if we preach the Goſpel, we muſt go to theſe private Meetings: which of theſe is indeed of greateſt moment to the glory of God, and the Peoples ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>In general,</hi> which is the greateſt matter, that the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus be preached, or the Union of our Pariſh Churches be promoted? <hi>In particular,</hi> whether ſhall any one of us who have a call on occaſion to preach at ſuch a time, place, or company, do more ſervice to God, by going and doing it, or by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing and going to our Pariſh-Church for the ſake of unity, for which we have ſtill other ſeaſons? And which is the <hi>greater evil,</hi> to have the people of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh only divided into ſeveral places to hear the Miniſters of both perſwaſions preach to them (when this too ſhall not hinder them being parts ſtill or members of the ſame Parochial ſociety;) or that all the Preachers and Miniſters in the Nation but thoſe only who <hi>Conform,</hi> ſhould have their mouths ſtopt, and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40985:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>buryed? How! when there is ſo many of them? ſo many of them truly ſerious and painful labourers? ſo many of them that actually do ſo much good, and the everlaſting welfare of thouſands mens ſouls depend upon it? What is <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> in compariſon? we will appeal to the Conſciences of every upright equal perſon, (whether Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt or Non-conformiſt) that fears God, to give Judgement. The preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, and <hi>particular Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies</hi> are of <hi>Divine: Parochial Churches</hi> are of <hi>Humane</hi> inſtitution. That which is Divine, is undeniably to be preferr'd before that which is of humane apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For the great charge then againſt us of Schiſme, we anſwer. Schiſm is a <hi>cauſeleſs ſeparation of the Churches union, a cauſeleſs ſeparation from her Communion,</hi> the Communion of a Church whereof we are Members, or ſhould be. Let any learned Man that hath read any thing about Schiſm, tell us, if we do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it right, by a ſeparation that is cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40985:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>for if there be a cauſe, the ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be juſtified, as it is between us, and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now when the Caſe between the Conformiſts and us is ſo open, and in the face of the Sun, that unleſs we <hi>ſet,</hi> and <hi>keep up</hi> theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>Conventicles,</hi> the whole Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Non-conformiſt Miniſters muſt be laid aſide from the Exerciſe of their Office, for ought we ſee as long as theſe Men do hold, whatſoever in the mean while becomes of the Souls of ſo many Multitudes: What Apology, Defence, or <hi>Account</hi> do we need more, but this only, <hi>Is there not a Cauſe?</hi> they are the words of <hi>David</hi> to his ſurly El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brethren, who are offended only for his being about the Buſineſs he was ſent. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>ſaid, what have I done? is there not a Cauſe!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Apology we know it will be ſaid by the Epiſcopal Party, (for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe that we know can be ſaid to any purpoſe) <hi>But you may conform.</hi> If ſo, we muſt then deſire of ſome one or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40985:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>other of the Learned and Conſcientious among them to contribute but this one thing towards it: A little thing we may think, if they could do it. It is only to anſwer the Sheet which was tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Parliament about two or three Seſſions ago, for taking away the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and <hi>Oxford</hi> Oath, and which ſhall be in order therefore by and by repeated. We would give all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in our Purſes, with a Tax, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any, upon condition that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament would either have ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ours anſwered, or elſe repeal their Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>There are Three things enjoyned in the Act of Uniformity. <hi>Re-ordination.</hi> The <hi>Declaration.</hi> The <hi>Subſcription.</hi> As we have borrowed thus much already from a late Paper of the Author now intimated: So ſhall we make uſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſame perſon, in the which follows.</p>
            <p>We begin with the Threſhold, <hi>Re-ordination.</hi> It muſt be acknowledg'd
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40985:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>by both Parties, That <hi>Re-ordinvtion</hi> is an uncouth thing, quite againſt the Hair of the literate World, whether Fathers, Councels, or Modern Divines, Proteſtants and Papiſts; and put uſually into the ſame Predicament (and more eſpecially by <hi>Austin</hi>) with Re-baptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If the preſent Biſhops therefore in the impoſing of it, would have ſtood by it, and maintained the Lawfulneſs of it, as being neither againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor poſitive Inſtitution; but as having rather the Examples of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> more particularly for it, with what elſe by ſome is urged, againſt the ſtream bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of humane Authority, this would perhaps have looked handſome, and the ingenuity of it would have been nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But when they would generally have it impoſed, and yet diſown it, and be aſhamed of it, in ſo much as though there be few or none ordained by Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, but believed the validity of that Ordination, they would have our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40985:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Miniſtry to be null, and make us contented in effect to be held but u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers of holy things, Sacrilegious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and all our Miniſterial Acts void, as the Acts of meer Laicks before, it is really ſo intollerably vile, as no mortal fleſh is able to bear. It is true, there is one Inſtance from Antiquity out of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> of ſome perſons with <hi>Iſchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> among them whom they would not allow (as theſe hold) to be Miniſters; becauſe one <hi>Coluthus,</hi> that ordained them, was only a Presbyter. Unto which may be added, the Story of the purblind Biſhop, 2. <hi>Concil. Hiſpal.</hi> 3. <hi>Can.</hi> 5. <hi>circa An.</hi> 656. But we anſwer with Dr. <hi>Field</hi> on the Church in his Fifth Book, It is one thing what they <hi>judged</hi> according to their <hi>Eccleſiastical Canons;</hi> and another what they <hi>ought to judg</hi> according to the Word of God. The Scripture makes no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Biſhop and Presbyter, the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority and Inferiority ariſing after in the Church: And when we are made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40985:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſts Miniſters, and put in office by him according to his <hi>Word,</hi> how ſhall that Authority be vacated for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting only in the <hi>Constitutions of Men?</hi> Here is a matter of Infinite wrong, which the opinion of theſe Men do us. It takes away the Office Chriſt hath given us, and holds it null. If it was a grievous thing in the late times to put one of theſe Miniſters out of his <hi>place,</hi> what is it to put ſo many of us out of our Office? There is no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon almoſt of Spirit, but will be ready to part with his life as ſoon as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he holds from the King; and ſhall not the Ordained Miniſter maintain the Right which he holds from Chriſt? When ſo many eminent Predeceſſors to theſe Biſhops, and other Defenders of this Church have maintained Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Ordination: When the Reformed Churches abroad have no other: When the Caſe was ſuch as that there was no other to be had <hi>here</hi> in the late times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When not we alone then are concerned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40985:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>only in the wrong, but our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> whoſe cauſe it is, and whoſe buſineſs we are to do, and the Souls of ſo many people: We cannot but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> in a matter of ſo great right and wrong as this is. For we are contented to have it reviſed, and judged, whether the <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhop be diſtinguiſhedly named in Chriſts Charter for Ordination, as he is in the Canons of Men: Or when we have been ordained already, as <hi>Timothy</hi> by the <hi>laying on of the hands of Presbytery,</hi> whether the <hi>Lawn</hi> be <hi>de Eſſentia</hi> to the Ceremony, and the Hands avail no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without the <hi>Sleeves</hi> on.</p>
            <p>The next thing is the Declaration. <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do here declare my unfained aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contain-and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcribed in and by the Book Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The Book of Common Prayer, and the form of Ordaining Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons.</hi> That is <hi>aſsent</hi> to all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing <hi>contained in,</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing <hi>preſcribed</hi> by theſe Books. Sirs,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40985:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>There was a time, when that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had the hopeful overture of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord between the ſober of two parties, and the Hearts of moſt Men were in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to receive it. But alas! in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſuch a Gratious and Bleſſed Iſſue as was expected, loe here the ſtreight injunction of an <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> to <hi>all</hi> Conformity, and <hi>every thing</hi> of it, new and old, to be approved and obeyed, or elſe one part of the Miniſtry muſt be immediately turn'd out. How can thoſe now whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are, and have been ſtill for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration between both opinions in times before as now, be able to come over to one ſide altogether on ſuch terms as theſe. How can they (we ſay) make ſo ſhort a turn as this, without the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of ſome ſprain to their Conſcience, if they do it? We cannot tell you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, nor are willing to declare the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions we have upon our Spirits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a going back from that more Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Plain, and ſimply zealous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40985:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Almighty God, in the way we were in, and <hi>Reformation</hi> we ſought, unto that ſomething we are not uſed to, and fear, <hi>to wit,</hi> unto a <hi>form of Worſhip and Diſcipline,</hi> that carrying a countenance of both, but being rather only a kind of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols thereof, doth ſeem to us, by the ſhew, pomp, and complement of the things it contains not, to undermine the Life, Power, and Efficacy of one and the other. We cannot tell you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps what moves us ſo much from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whether fear of Popery returning on us, or <hi>aliquid</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: But we will produce Two or Three Inſtances apiece, againſt <hi>Aſſent,</hi> and againſt <hi>Conſent</hi> to that which is injoyned, that we may approve our ſelves to the Conſciences of <hi>all,</hi> as well as our <hi>own,</hi> in refuſing this Declaration.</p>
            <p>For our <hi>Aſſent.</hi> In the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed we find this paſſage, <hi>Which Faith, except every one does keep whole, without doubt he ſhall periſh everlaſtingly.</hi> One
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40985:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Articles of this Creed is this. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt is of the Father and the Son.</hi> In this Article we know the Greek Church hath differed from the Latin, and held, That the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> proceeds from the <hi>Father</hi> only. If we give our <hi>Aſſent</hi> then to <hi>every thing</hi> or <hi>paſſage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Book,</hi> we muſt believe the Greek Church <hi>undoubtedly damned.</hi> And what if ſome of the Non-conformiſts (as well as of Conformiſts) do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it not impoſſible, but that ſome <hi>Heathen,</hi> and profeſſed Socinian may be ſaved? What if they cannot think o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in regard to the Goodneſs of God, but that whoſoever he was, or is, that walk'd, or walks up to his Light in ſincerity, with a general Repentance for his unſeen Errors, muſt by vertue of the Covenant made with <hi>Adam</hi> faln, and <hi>Noah,</hi> no leſs than the <hi>Jews</hi> were by the ſame confirmed with <hi>Abraham,</hi> be in a ſtate of acceptation with God, not conceiving but both alike (for ought they ſee) were ignorant of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40985:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Redemption by the Blood of Chriſt, or the means how their Peace was made with him? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>We have ſhewn before that Chriſt is the first begotten of God, the Divine Reaſon, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Word, whereof the whole kind of Men, or the whole ſtock of Mankind do partake; and whoſoever lives according to reaſon, are Chriſtians, though they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Heathen, and without God, ſuch as</hi> Socrates, Heraclitus, <hi>and the like, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Martyr</hi> in his ſecond Apology for the Chriſtians: We do not ſay we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this, nor deny it: But we are ready to ſay what was <hi>Luthers</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>We hope God will be merciful to ſuch a one as</hi> Cicero, <hi>but our Duty is to abide by the Word.</hi> And yet cannot this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Candour it ſelf be uſed, if we muſt be forced to declare, that whoſoever believes not the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, muſt undoubtedly periſh. Not that other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40985:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Non conformiſts generally make any ſcruple in this: But what do thoſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and learned Doctors of the Church think of it, who have a name given them upon this account, that though they hold ſome things that agree not with her Articles or Homilies, yet they can conform to them, or have a <hi>Latitude</hi> to do it? <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do declare my unfained Aſſent and Conſent to every thing contained in the Book of Common Prayer;</hi> and yet I <hi>A. B.</hi> do declare that I Aſſent not to that paſſage in the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed. Again, I <hi>A. B.</hi> do profeſs that a Heathen may be ſaved; and yet I do <hi>libenter &amp; ex animo</hi> ſubſcribe to the Article among the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine, that does pronounce him <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed,</hi> who dares hold ſuch an opinion. We are not ignorant indeed, how ſome would blend the two terms <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> and then interpret them by the words <hi>[to the uſe]</hi> in the Act: But this is a ſhift which will not ſatisfie all perſons, and many deſire to uſe no ſhifts. If theſe words <hi>[to the uſe]</hi> had been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40985:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>put into the Declaration it ſelf, it had been better: Yet if they had, <hi>Aſſent</hi> is proper to the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> And yet moreover, how can a Man unfainedly conſent to the uſe of any ſuch Particular which is falſe, and which perhaps he even abhors, that the Wiſe and Ingenious of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler perſwaſion ſhould think he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved. Another Inſtance ſhall be this. In the Service on the <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon,</hi> we thank God for <hi>preſerving the King, and the Three Eſtates of the Realm Aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</hi> It is a difficult Point now in the Politicks of <hi>England,</hi> Whether the <hi>Three Eſtates</hi> be, the King, the Houſe of Lords, and the Houſe of Commons: Or the Lords-Spiritual, Temporal, and Commons. The late King made no ſcruple in his Anſwer to the <hi>nineteen Propoſitions</hi> to reckon himſelf one of the Three Eſtates: Neither was there any we know that durſt account the Three Eſtates of the Land to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when the Biſhops were turned out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40985:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Houſe by an Act. We cannot tell therefore of what Conſequence it is to the fundimental liberty, conſtitution, and ſtate of the Kingdom, to yield unto the inſinuation of ſuch a thing as this in our Prayers. No Man can give his unfained Aſſent to any thing he knows not, and underſtands not. This is a thing we do not know that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are indeed <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>Three Eſtates</hi> of this Realm. Whether they be or no, we diſpute not; but till we are better ſatisfied with them and their ſtation, we are afraid that any ſnare ſhould be laid for the people in the Exerciſe of their Devotions unto God. We muſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one Particular more, which is our general Exception. In the new Book there is inſerted ſeveral Paſſages that make the Biſhops a diſtinct Office and Order from the Presbyter. We need not name the Words, for they are put in more than once <hi>de induſtria.</hi> They would not be content with a difference in <hi>Degree</hi> and <hi>Eminency;</hi> but they would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40985:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>have us declare to a <hi>jure divino</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, diſproved by learned Doctors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Papiſts, and among the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Men, as well as the Reformed Churches. Now we humbly beſeech the Parliament to conſider, whether the Biſhops have dealt candidly with us to get ſuch a Condition impoſed on the Presbyterian to the keeping of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, as not only Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> but ſuch as Dr. <hi>Field</hi> and <hi>Francis Maſon</hi> muſt have been turned out for Non-conformiſts upon the ſame. <hi>There are Two Orders Eccleſiastical, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri &amp; Diaconi. When we ſay Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, we name but two Orders, yet three Degrees.</hi> Mr. <hi>Joſeph Mede</hi> diſc. V.</p>
            <p>For our <hi>Conſent.</hi> We will name three things likewiſe (and but name them) more indefinitely. There is the <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy,</hi> or Biſhop inveſted with ſole power of Ordination, and Jurisdiction. There are the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> in general ſo often diſputed. There is the <hi>Impoſition
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40985:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſelf</hi> of things not neceſſary, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſtumbling to many good Men, and cauſe of our diviſions. If we give our unfained conſent <hi>to all and every thing preſcribed by the Book of Common Prayer, and the form of ordering Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons,</hi> then muſt we give our approbation (we ſuppoſe) to theſe things amongſt others. But if the Two firſt are diſputable, we are paſt doubt in the laſt, that to impoſe things that are inductive to others to ſin, and yet not neceſſary, is unlawful. <hi>What Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath Christ given to the Church to bind Men up to more than himſelf hath done?</hi> Says <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> with much more to the purpoſe, in his Epiſtle to his <hi>Irani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum?</hi> We will not ſpeak ſo laxly alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as he does there; but when we diſtinguiſh the <hi>Impoſition</hi> and <hi>Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> this we are fully perſwaded of in Conſcience, that the <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to the things impoſed may perhaps be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; the <hi>Impoſition</hi> of them is not to be ſo, neither by that Dr. nor by us;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40985:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40985:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:40985:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>For if we build again the things we have deſtroyed, we make our ſelves tranſgreſſors.</hi> It is not (Sirs!) the ſerving God by a Liturgy, or the reading Common Prayer in the ordinary daily Service that makes us Non-conformiſts, though it be this only lyes in the view of the inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>many,</hi> and though there are ſome things we except againſt the occaſional Offices, which by and by may be named. We are ſorry if any have given cauſe for ſuch a ſcandal which tends to the breaking of the Concord and Charity which ought to be maintained equally between the Brethren of our <hi>private,</hi> and of the Parochial Congregations. We ſhould be ready to do any thing we could to the healing this ſcandal. But there are matters of another moment, which if we had liberty to open to the World at large as our cauſe requires. We doubt not but that it might come to ſee, whether we have reaſon to ſtick at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity or no. There are few of us who are not ſenſible in ſome meaſure of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40985:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>corruption which hath crept into the Church in regard to the diſcipline or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it by the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan</hi> Biſhop ſo much degenerated ſince <hi>Cyprians</hi> time from the primitive ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city: And there hath paſſed a ſolemn Oath over the Nation, engaging the main Body of it to the endeavour of a Reformation. Now when the ſame government is returned upon the Land with all its former corruptions, and more heavy Injunctions, if we ſhould generally ſubmit again to it without obtaining any amendment, compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or abatement, we dread to think on it, with what <hi>faces</hi> they ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand before God, who have lift up their <hi>hands</hi> to him for things quite contrary in the late Revolutions. But to proceed, at laſt, Beſides the <hi>matter</hi> of this Declaration, the ſtrict preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as to the form of words is more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to be noted, <hi>That this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be made in theſe words and no other.</hi> And what if a Miniſter would read the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40985:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Book of Common Prayer without this Declaration? Or what if he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the contents of the Book in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Expreſſions? Why ſhould theſe crooked SS's be ramm'd down the Throat to choak any? If we were put to declare in this form of words to any Book we know of this Bulk, even to the Bible it ſelf (as to any Copies we have yet ſeen of it) we muſt, for ought we ſee, ſtill ſtick out. It is ſaid in the <hi>Kings,</hi> That <hi>Ahazia</hi> was <hi>two and twenty years old</hi> when he began to Reign, and in the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> that he was <hi>two and forty:</hi> Both theſe cannot be true: If we were put therefore to Declare in theſe words, and no other, <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do declare my Aſſent to every thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in our Bible,</hi> we ſhould be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd: For we cannot <hi>Aſſent</hi> to the <hi>Truth</hi> of both theſe places in the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> nor <hi>Conſent</hi> to the errour of the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription or Tranſlation, when we know not otherwiſe how to reconcile the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in them. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. <hi>v.</hi> 28.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40985:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>our Pſalter reads the words thus, <hi>And they were not obedient to his Word;</hi> our Bible reads them, <hi>And they rebelled not against his Word.</hi> We argue here. One Particular contained in the Book of Common Prayer is the Tranſlation of the Text. But if the Tranſlation be true in the Pſalter, it is falſe in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: And if it be true in the Bible, it is falſe in the Pſalter. That they <hi>rebelled,</hi> and <hi>rebelled</hi> not, no Man can give his <hi>Aſſent.</hi> We know indeed how the words may be true in both Tranſlations, as to the <hi>minds of the Tranſlators,</hi> the one referring them to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the other to the <hi>Aegyptians:</hi> But we urge this more ſtrictly. The mind of the Text it ſelf, of the Holy Ghoſt, or <hi>Davids</hi> mind whoſe Pſalm it is, was but one: While the Tranſlators then are contrary in their minds, both of them cannot have <hi>Davids</hi> mind; and ſo one of the Tranſlations muſt have that meaning which is falſe. And why muſt we be made then to give our <hi>Conſent</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40985:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>that both theſe Tranſlations ſhould be uſed, when the falſe may be amended by the right? We mention this little thing among many others that have been objected by Non-conformiſts here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, to ſhew the inſuperable incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of theſe continued Injunctions. There is one ſuch a little thing more, which perhaps hath not yet been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly offered. It is the Rule preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us for the finding out the moveable Feaſts and Holy-days. <hi>Eaſter-day, on which the reſt depend, is always the first Sunday after the firſt Full Moon, which happens next after the one and twentieth day of</hi> March. Now examine this Rule for the laſt Year 1674. and you will find the firſt Full Moon after the 21th. of <hi>March</hi> was upon the 10th. of <hi>April,</hi> and conſequently if this Rule hold good, the next <hi>Sunday,</hi> which was <hi>April</hi> the 12th. ſhould have been <hi>Eaſter-day:</hi> But <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-day</hi> was upon the 19th. of <hi>April,</hi> as the <hi>Table for</hi> 40 <hi>years</hi> in the Common-Prayer does tell you, as well as our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40985:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Almanacks did. Well! And how then ſhall we declare our Aſſent and Conſent <hi>to all and every thing contained</hi> in this Book? The Table is in the Book, and the Rule is in the Book. If the Rule be true, the Table is falſe: If the Table be true, the Rule is falſe. It is a grievous Caſe, that we muſt be turned out of our Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe we cannot give our Aſſent and Conſent to <hi>Both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having mentioned theſe leſſer things in the way, we ſhall perhaps be blamed, if we neglect ſome other, that are of more notice and moment with our Brethren.</p>
            <p>In the Office of Baptiſm, the Parents are not admitted to covenant for their Children, and how ſhall the Infant an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <hi>Credo, Abrenuntio,</hi> out of the mouth of the Godfather? It is the Parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Covenant that gives Title to the Childs Baptiſm, and unleſs the Father or Mother make ſuch a profeſſion, as that we can probably judge the one or the other thereby to be in Covenant,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40985:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>we cannot (ſome of us) admit the Children to Baptiſm, nor themſelves to the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>In the Burial; how ſhall we be able for our lives to ſay of every one that dies Un-excommunicate in the Pariſh, that <hi>God of his great Mercy hath taken his Soul unto himſelf,</hi> with ſuch like Expreſſions? Or that it is <hi>certain by Gods Word</hi> that every Child Baptized before Actual Sin, is in a ſtate of Salvation? Let our Learned <hi>Gataker</hi> be conſulted, <hi>De Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis Infantilis vi &amp; Efficacia,</hi> and then judge of it who will.</p>
            <p>In the Service for the Holy-days, there ale the moſt of us not agreed upon the Lawfulneſs of ſuch days, <hi>Six days ſhall thou labour:</hi> But above all the reſt, there is one thing in S <hi>Clements</hi> day preſcrib'd by the New Common-Prayer Book, that we wonder how thoſe themſelves that put it in can give their conſent to it, which is, the change of a profitable Chapter in <hi>Eſay</hi> for the Story (God defend us!) or <hi>Bell,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40985:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>There is laſtly the uſe of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> a compleat Inſtitution of it ſelf, brought in or added to the Ordinance of Chriſt, appearing to be of the ſame nature and end. This, we doubt, does entrench upon his Kingly Office, and muſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly therefore offer one reaſon for the removal, which we ſollicite whatſoever be done in other matters. <hi>The Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in uſe amongſt us</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>) <hi>are retained in no other reſpect ſaving only for that to retain them is to our ſeeming good and profitable.</hi> To which purpoſe, <hi>We are content with theſe only</hi> (ſays the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book) <hi>as be apt to stir up the dull mind of Man to remembrance of his duty,</hi> by ſome edifying ſignification. But the Croſs being a Ceremony ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to Children who are uncapable of having <hi>their minds ſtirred up</hi> by any thing ſignified thereby, it is manifeſtly <hi>retained without their profit.</hi> We will enforce the Argument. By the ſame reaſon as we retain the Croſs in Baptiſm, the other Ceremonies in Popery which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40985:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>are left may be readmitted. As we uſe the <hi>Croſs</hi> to ſignifie that the Child muſt <hi>fight manfully under Christs Banner,</hi> we may uſe the <hi>Chriſm</hi> wherein the Croſs was uſed to be made, to ſignifie the Chriſtians <hi>anointing</hi> to the Combate, and ſo forward. There is nothing can be replyed hereto in good earneſt, but that it is true if the Church pleaſed to enjoyn it, ſo we might. We urge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, By the ſame reaſon as the Church hath relinquiſht the Chriſm in Baptiſm, it may leave the Croſs alſo, that is only if it pleaſe ſo to vote in a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Convocation. And that it ſhould do ſo, there is cauſe enough, if there were nothing elſe, to be ſaid but this only, that as for all other Ceremonies enjoyned, the Conformiſts may plead, that they are but <hi>Circumſtances of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> wherein the Church hath proper Authority to appoint what is decent and orderly: But for any ſolemn intire Rite, which is no <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of the Ordinance unto which it is appended,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40985:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>or any ways <hi>in genere neceſſary</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, if this alſo be enjoyned, we ſhall have no bottom or banks ſet to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Ceremonies, how far this Sea ſhall go, and no farther than ſo.</p>
            <p>We will heap no more matters of this kind, for they are infinite: And it is ſome relief to our thoughts, that the Parliament (we thank God) did come to be a little ſenſible of it, in ſo much as they were near content one Seſſion to Caſhier this Declaration quite. There does remain now therefore the Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and this queſtion which will ariſe upon it. <hi>Whether there be not as good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in regard to the most ſober Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to take away this ſubſcripttion in the Act of uniformity, and the Oath in the</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford <hi>Ast, as well as the Declaration of Aſſent and Conſent?</hi> and here making firſt our humble Proteſtation, that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend nothing hereby but loyally to the Government, we muſt preſent the Sheet before mentioned to their renewed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:40985:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Subſcription is this. <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do declare, That it is not lawful upon any Pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King. And that I do abhor that Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Poſition of taking Arms by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or thoſe Commiſſionated by him: And that I will conform to the Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now by Law eſtabliſh'd. And I do declare, That I do hold there lyes no Obligation upon me, or any other perſon, from the Oath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the ſolemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to endeavour any change or alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Government either in Church or State: And that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawfull Oath, and impoſed upon the Subjects of the Realm againſt the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom.</hi> The Oath this. <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſwear, That it is not lawful upon any Pretence whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to take Arms againſt the King. And that I abhor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by his Authority against his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by him in purſuance of ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40985:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>And that I will not at any time endeavour any alteration of Government either in Church or State.</hi> In this Oath and Subſcription, we have the <hi>matter,</hi> and the <hi>form</hi> of words; that is, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the Compoſure. The one whereof, and the other in both are lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the enſuing Exceptions. Which we deſire may be taken with Candor in reſpect only to our deſign, that is as <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative</hi> for the removal of theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions: Not as peremptorily <hi>defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> of our own judgments, and much leſs of others above our Sphear in all the Caſes contained in them.</p>
            <p>To begin with the Oath. Here are three parts of it. The firſt part appears not (for we ſpeak it humbly only, and argumentatively) conſiſtent with <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> the ſecond with <hi>Truth;</hi> nor the third with <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will take up the laſt part firſt. <hi>And I will not endeavour any alteration of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment.</hi> There is no Government on Earth ſo perfect that it hath need of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40985:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Laws like the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment may be conſidered in the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration</hi> or the <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> The word <hi>Government</hi> here is ſet down inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely, without diſtinction. Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Laws, and ſo Government in the Adminiſtration, is as neceſſary many times upon emergent occaſions to the <hi>Body politick,</hi> as the freſh Air is to the <hi>natural.</hi> This Oath was brought into the Houſe to have been made Common. It were not a thing righteous to have had that engagement laid on perſons in ſuch a capacity: It is not righteous to have it laid on any that are Free-holders; and free Subjects as we are. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our Nation, as Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is ſuch that no Law can be <hi>eſtabliſh'd</hi> or <hi>repealed,</hi> but it muſt paſs the Houſe of Commons, and ſo the whole Body doth concur in their repreſentatives to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry alteration of Government (or in the Government) that is made, if it be legal: And no houſe of Commons are choſen but by the people. <hi>Every</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40985:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>is inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d to be there preſent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in perſon, or by procuration, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people is taken to be every mans conſent,</hi> ſays Sir <hi>Thomas Smith de Rep. Angl. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Nay, <hi>while the King</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio &amp; aſſenſu Baronum leges olim im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuit univerſo Regno, <hi>by the counſel and aſſent of his Barons did give Laws to his whole Realm,</hi> conſentire inferior quiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> viſus eſt in perſona Domini ſui Capitalis prout hodie per procuratores Comita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, <hi>every Inferior ſeemed to conſent in the perſon of his chief Lord, as now they do by their Burgeſſes and Knights of the Shires,</hi> ſays Sir <hi>Henry Spelman.</hi> This is ſo true, that in this ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> is, that the Laws that paſs are ſaid to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Quas vulgus elegerit, Which the people ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll chooſe.</hi> Now then if every free Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t hath a fundamental liberty to chooſe K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ights and Burgeſſes, and accordingly to inform them of their Grievances, and petition them for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, and in them, as their Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives, do conſent to the alteration of Government and Laws (if there be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40985:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>any) as profitable to the Nation. How can ſuch an Oath be impoſed on him, <hi>That he will not endeavour any alteration,</hi> as this is? Is not chooſing Burgeſſes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming them, petitioning them, acting and legal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y conſenting in them to that end <hi>an endeavour?</hi> and that as much as can be in their Place and Calling? And no more than an Endeavour <hi>in their Place and Calling</hi> was challenged by any. It is true, the <hi>new</hi> Laws may be <hi>made,</hi> and <hi>old repealed,</hi> without alteration of the <hi>Conſtitution:</hi> But not without <hi>alteration of Government;</hi> becauſe Government takes in both the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> and the <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> Let us ſuppoſe therefore the word <hi>Government</hi> confined only to the Conſtitution. There is the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Government in the <hi>State,</hi> which is a <hi>Legal Monarchy,</hi> and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we are ſo far bound from endeavouring to alter, as that we think it is not alterable by the <hi>King</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and <hi>Parliament;</hi> becauſe that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power for the Adminiſtration
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40985:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>muſt be ſuppoſed in all Communities, to be derived from, and held by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution.</hi> But as for Government in the <hi>Church,</hi> we are to know and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that the Conſtitution hereof it ſelf is but a Law of the Adminiſtration, in reference to the <hi>State.</hi> And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently when all Laws for the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration are liable to the Regulation of Parliaments, the great queſtion will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, how thoſe Men who are Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian or Independent in their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and think Epiſcopacy againſt the Scripture can be abridged the <hi>Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> only afore-mentioned, (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts but in chooſing Repreſentatives, and doing no more than the Conſitution allows) in order to the proſecution of what they think themſelves obliged to in Conſcience, both by <hi>Oath,</hi> and <hi>the Word of God?</hi> Is not the foundation Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the whole People, and our ſelves with them here in danger? Judg ye that are wiſe. And what an anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Plot have we had here on the Nation,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40985:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>that <hi>Allegiance</hi> in effect ſhould be ſworn to the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as well as to the <hi>King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Words</hi> then (or <hi>Form</hi>) we wonder at this Rigour in the Compiler, that a Man muſt ſwear not to endeavour <hi>any</hi> Alteration. Had it not been enough to be engaged, not to endeavour the Alteration of the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in the Church, and <hi>Monarchy</hi> in the State, but muſt it be <hi>not any Alteration?</hi> It were well we were ſo abſolutely perfect. And again, muſt they not at <hi>any time</hi> endeavour any alteration? What if times ſhould turn, and we be in as great a confuſion as we were, or any the like chance or change come? Muſt theſe Men be bound up that they cannot endeavour to reduce back this Government that we have? No, not the King and Biſhops, if the Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the times ſhould put them out; for they have ſworn, they will not <hi>at any time endeavour any alteration in Church or State.</hi> Sirs! The <hi>matter</hi> of this obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being againſt the fundamental Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40985:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Subject and Parliament, and the words you ſee ſo enſnaring, and that againſt the duty all owe to the publick good: We offer it you to conſider in the firſt place, whether this <hi>laſt part</hi> be according to <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>middle part</hi> of the Oath. Here is a <hi>poſition</hi> of taking Arms <hi>by the Kings authority againſt any Commiſſionated by him,</hi> which muſt be ſworn to, as <hi>abhord and traiterous.</hi> There is now a Caſe in the mouths of all the underſtanding Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers of the Oath and Subſcription. Suppoſe ſome <hi>Writ</hi> ſued out, and comes to the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> hands, and ſuppoſe ſome to oppoſe the Execution by the Kings Perſonal Command or Commiſſion, and he thereupon raiſes the <hi>poſſe Comitatus</hi> upon them. We will ask here, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Sheriff</hi> acts not herein by the Kings Authority? We think it cannot be denyed. <hi>By the Kings Authority is all one as by the Law, or in the Name of the King according to Law.</hi> And when he can act ſo againſt any for all their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40985:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the Law will bear him out, how is this <hi>poſition</hi> in this Caſe <hi>traiterus,</hi> and to be <hi>abhord?</hi> for our parts we do reſolutely believe that it was not ever the intent of the Parliament in this Oath, or the Subſcription, (as to the Major part we may be bold) to advance the perſonal <hi>Will</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion</hi> of the King above <hi>Law,</hi> which were to make his power <hi>deſpotical,</hi> and not <hi>Royal. Non eſt Rex</hi> (ſays <hi>Bracton</hi>) <hi>ubi dominatur voluntas, non Lex, He is no King that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns by his will, and not by the Law.</hi> And how this <hi>poſition</hi> indefinitely (without exception of this Caſe at leaſt) muſt be ſworn to as altogether traiterous, we are to learn. What if any ſhould come with a Commiſſion under the Seal to raiſe Money without an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by vertue of ſuch Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall ſeize our Goods, rifle our Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and raviſh our Wives? May not the People, or our inferiour Magiſtrates, or the Sheriff for the County, withſtand ſuch violence? May not the Conſtable
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40985:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>alone by a Warrant from the Juſtice to keep the Peace, raiſe the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and do it? If he may, or the Sheriff may, it muſt be in the Name of the King, or by Authority of the Law; and then is there ſome Caſe or Caſes where Arms or Force may be raiſed by the Authority of the King againſt ſuch as are Commiſſionated by him, though never againſt his own Sacred Perſon. Suppoſe again that Papiſts or Fanaticks ſhould either by Power or Surprize, at any time get the King into their hands, (as the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> once dealt with the <hi>French</hi> King) and prevail with him for fear of his life to grant Commiſſions under His Hand and Seal deſtructive to the Church and State, muſt the Nation be remedileſs in this Caſe, and ſo the King and Kingdom ruin'd by theſe Commiſſions? Nay, what ſecurity hath the Nation, that a Lord Keeper may not prove Traytor to his King, and Countrey? If we may ſuppoſe ſuch a thing poſſible, what if ſuch a Lord Keeper ſhould under the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40985:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Broad Seal grant Commiſſions to disband His Majeſties Life Guard, deliver up the Navy or Sea-port Towns, ſeize the Tower or places of ſtrength; in what a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were the King and Kingdom brought, if the Subjects hands be bound up by an Oath not to reſiſt or take Arms, againſt the execution of ſuch Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Suppoſe but ſo long as till they underſtand his deſign, for by that time, the whole Nation may be paſt recovery. We are offended at the ſenſe, and ſtand amazed at the horrour of thoſe ſad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences into which the Impoſition of ſuch like <hi>Teſts,</hi> or Injunctions as theſe, (if not timely retrenched) may lead our Poſterity. <hi>The Courts of Law can avoid the Kings Charters or Commiſſions which are paſſed againſt Law, for the King is ſubject to the Law, and Sworn to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it,</hi> ſays Judg <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his Works, <hi>p.</hi> 48. As for the <hi>form</hi> then of the <hi>words, I abhor this Traiterous Poſition,</hi> they are harſh, the word <hi>abhor</hi> eſpecially is a word of intereſt and paſſion, a cooler
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40985:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>word, as I <hi>diſown</hi> or diſallow, might have ſerved. Some of the more Grave (as <hi>Calamy</hi> particularly) were much offended at that word. A Man may ſay a thing is unlawful in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, when he cannot ſay according to truth, <hi>I abhor it.</hi> There is never a Gentleman in the Land but may ſwear truly, that he believes it unlawful to company with any other Woman as his own Wife; but if each one was put to ſwear he <hi>abhors it,</hi> we ſuppoſe ſome very good Sons of the Church, as well as our Brethren, would be found willing to be Non-conformiſts to ſuch an Oath. Well Sirs! when theſe words <hi>Abhor</hi> and <hi>Traiterous</hi> are ſo harſh in the <hi>Compoſure,</hi> and when ſuch Caſes as above mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned may be put as to the poſition in the <hi>matter</hi> of it, wherein it ſeems juſtifiable, and without offence: We offer it in the next place to conſideration, whether this <hi>middle part</hi> of the Oath and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription be according to <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40985:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>For the <hi>firſt part,</hi> We have a large Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion roundly ſworn. The Oath and Subſcription runs not only, that it is not lawful to take Arms againſt the King, or that it is not lawful on any pretence, but <hi>on any pretence</hi> (or cauſe) <hi>what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</hi> The Grammatical literal conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that word ſeems to intimate no leſs than that this Propoſition muſt be held without reſtraint or limitation. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the moſt emment of Authors which have wrote of the Power of Princes, and eſtabliſh'd it againſt Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in their writings on this Subject, we ſuppoſe there are ſew or none to be valued above theſe Three, <hi>Bareley, Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Arniſaeus.</hi> And we ſhall und, that they have all their reſtrictions or caſes of Exceptions in the maintenance of this Tenet. And how ſhall any be over earneſt here in puniſhing the Refuſer, when if the matter be well ſcan'd, the reaſon perhaps, why he refuſes, will be ſound only becauſe he hath read more then ſome others that yield their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40985:29"/>We begin with <hi>Barcley,</hi> that is <hi>William Barcley,</hi> a <hi>Scot</hi> and Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to the <hi>French</hi> King, who writes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Buchanan, Boucher,</hi> and other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchomachiſts, as he calls them. This learned Man endeavours to make his Prince to be above the whole People, that conſequently no Arms can be taken againſt him: Nevertheleſs, when he comes to put ſome preſſing Caſes, he thus limits himſelf. <hi>Quid ergo? nulli ne Caſus incidere poſſunt, quibus populo in Rigem arma capere jure ſuo liceat? nulli certe quanidiu Rex manet. What then? Can there no Cafes happen, wherein it is lawful for the people to take Arms againſt the King by Right? None certainly ſo long as he remains a King.</hi> There are Caſes indeed he accounts in which a King doth <hi>Exuere perſonam Regis,</hi> or <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natu ſe exuere, Put off the Perſon of a King.</hi> And particularly (<hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 16.) he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Two. <hi>Si regnum alienet, ſi Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicam evertere conatur. If he go to alienate his Kingdom, if he go to overthrew
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40985:30"/>the Common-wealth.</hi> We cannot tell how to approve this Doctrine; the Papiſts uſe the ſame we know in another Caſe, we may not fight againſt our King; but if the Pope Excommunicate him, he ſhall be no King with them. Let us come to <hi>Grotius,</hi> and firſt quote him in his Judgment of <hi>Barcley,</hi> leſt you may think elſe we miſtake him. <hi>Barclaius</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Regii impariilicet aſſertor fortiſſimus huc tamen deſcendit, ut populo &amp; inſigni ejus parti jus concedit ſe tuendi adverſus immanem ſaevitiam.</hi> Barcley, <hi>though the moſt aſſertor of Kingly Government, does come to this, that he grants a Right to the People, or the moſt eminent part of them, of defending themſelves againſt intollerable oppreſſion.</hi> For himſelf then after he hath aſſerted this Tenet, <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum impurium tenentibus jure reſiſti non poſſe; That the higher Powers may not lawfully be reſiſted,</hi> from Scripture, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, Authority, and Example, to as much purpoſe perhaps as any, he deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends to put ſeven Caſes, wherein he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40985:30"/>does <hi>Lectorem monere, ne putet in bane legem delinquere eos qui revera non delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quunt; Warn his Reader, leſt he miſtake ſome for delinquents that are not.</hi> For <hi>Arniſaeus,</hi> he hath wrote Three learned Books of Politicks. <hi>De Jure Majeſtatis. De Doctrina Politica. De Authoritate princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum in populum ſemper Inviolabile, ſeu, quod nulla ex cauſa ſubditis fas ſit contra legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum principem arma ſumere. That the Authority of Princes over the People, ought to be inviolable, or that it is lawful for no cauſe to take up Arms against our lawful Prince.</hi> Here then we have our Tenet, in the ſtate whereof he comes in the iſſue to dinguiſh between <hi>Rex</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannus,</hi> a <hi>King</hi> and a <hi>Tyrant, Tyrannus in Titulo, &amp; Tyrannus in Exercitio; A Tyrant in Title, and in Practiſe:</hi> And <hi>Tyrannus in Exercitio, A Tyrant in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe,</hi> he accounts does <hi>Excidere de Jure, etſi Haereditario, Fall from his Right, though Hereditary. Traditur Reſpublica Principi in eum finem</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ut illi praeſit in ſalutem omnium, a quo ſi prorſus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40985:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſciverit, etiam de poteſtate cadit, quum non alto fine ſibi commiſſum habebat. The Common-wealth is delivered to the Prince, that he ſhould rule over it for the common ſafety; from which if he depart altogether, he falls even from the Power it ſelf, which was committed to him only for this end.</hi> We do not give our conſent to, not paſs our cenſure upon the words we cite, but by ſuch Teſtimonies as theſe without naming others, we would convince thoſe perſons who were the Compilers of theſe Declarations to be ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or ſworn, with ſome reſentment and ſhame, that when the temperate ſenſe and meaning of them is ſuch as we were not like to boggle at, they ſhould be yet compoſed ſo <hi>in terminis,</hi> as to be obnoxious to ſo grand Exception. For the <hi>form</hi> then yet of the <hi>Words. I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſwear that it is not lawful,</hi> &amp;c. Here is an Oath to the <hi>matter of a Propoſition questioned,</hi> to the determination of a Point of Conſcience, and that diverſly decided. An Oath ſhould be to a <hi>matter
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40985:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>of fact,</hi> and cannot be taken but to that whereof we are certain. To require of Men therefore to ſwear to the verity of a Doctrinal Propoſition, is not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Judgment,</hi> being a thing impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe no Man is <hi>inſellible.</hi> Now then Sirs! When here is ſuch an <hi>Erratum</hi> in the Compoſure, as the want of the words <hi>I believe,</hi> or the like, <hi>I ſwear that I held or believe, that it is not lawful,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo material an Exception, as the Judgment of the moſt learned in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral comes to, againſt the Subſtance <hi>in Terminis,</hi> of the <hi>first</hi> part of this Oath, which yet gods down ordinarily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out chewing; we humbly oder it in the third place to be conſidered how this Oath can be taken either in <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Judgment.</hi> An Oath muſt be taken in Judgment, in Truth, and in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The <hi>first part</hi> (we argue) is not according to <hi>Judgment;</hi> The <hi>ſecond</hi> not according to <hi>Truth;</hi> The <hi>third</hi> not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> We ſpeak it humbly by way only of Argumentation
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40985:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>(as we have ſaid) craving pardon if it offend, for the manner of the Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We proceed to the <hi>Subſcription</hi> conjoyned, which hath we count Two Parts. The <hi>one</hi> is the purport wholly of the Oath; whereof therefore we ſhall adde no more but this, That when the <hi>matter</hi> of the one, and the other in the former part, is ſuch as enters the foundation of Politicks in general, and the Laws and State of the Land in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular (which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>), <hi>a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom regulated by Laws,</hi> as Sir <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> hath it: <hi>Rex ſub Deo &amp; Loge, The King is under God and the Law,</hi> ſays <hi>Hooker</hi> and <hi>Brecton:</hi>) So that it requires the skill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the greateſt <hi>Judges, Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants</hi> and: <hi>ages</hi> of the Law to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Caſes included in it, every poor ſilly Miniſter is put to decide the ſame for himſelf, and to have that evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence therein, as to be able to take his Cath, or give his Hand to the certainty of it. the <hi>other</hi> part of the Subſcription concer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s the <hi>Covenant,</hi> where the words
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40985:32"/>
               <hi>[nor any other]</hi> are ſuch a <hi>Ford</hi> (that as to the Conſciences of all not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Epiſcopal) ſo far as we ſee is unpaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it is nothing to ſome of our ſelves to ſubſcribe, <hi>there lyes no obligation on me from the Covenant to endeavour any alteration of Government,</hi> becauſe we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver took it, and was againſt our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and we can conceive for others in a <hi>private capacity,</hi> what have they to do with Government? No Oath can bind to ſedition and diſobedience. But as for ſuch as are in a <hi>publick capacity,</hi> and can act lawfully towards <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in their <hi>place,</hi> what ſhall we ſay to thoſe? One way there is indeed, will ſtrike off all quite, and that is to hold the preſent Government eſtabliſh'd to be <hi>Jure Divino</hi> altogether, ſo that any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration is ſin. He that holds thus, may affirm clearly, that though a Man ſwore he would endeavour to alter the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, it binds him nothing, let him be in what capacity he will, the leaſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40985:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>afteration is unlawful, and he muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repent of his Oath, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it. But if a Man hold, that the Presbyterian Government is rather <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> or that neither Epiſcopal nor Presbyterian is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> or that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Government is well, yet that <hi>ours,</hi> as it is not, is not altogether ſo well, but that ſomething may be alter'd for: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e better: We wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med how ſuch a Man can abſolve him who is in a <hi>publick capacity</hi> (as a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Man) from his endeavouring ſo much according to time and prudence, if he hath ſworn before that he will. It is in vain to hide where the water ſticks. There are ſome cannot tell how to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve <hi>one other</hi> for their ſins. They ſay not there lyes an obligation upon any other to do as they have ſworn, for fear it be dangerous; and they dare not ſay there lyes none, for fear of their Conſetences. As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o our ſelves this we may ſay, that we deſire to be inſtructed, and this we will ſay, that it is an hard
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40985:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>thing to put on it to ſay, that there lyes no obligation upon any other but our ſelves whether there does or no. We will therefore cloſe up our reaſons for Non-conformity, with this one Note only. If there be ſo many difficulties in <hi>one</hi> of the things only, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to Conformity, what a <hi>River</hi> hath he to <hi>wade,</hi> that muſt paſs through <hi>All</hi> together that belongs to it? We deſcend to ſome Propoſals for concord or mutual quiet to the Nation, under theſe Differences: And here alſo we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated with our <hi>Plough</hi> and <hi>Heifer</hi> from the ſame Author. <hi>Secundae cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes prudentius &amp; moderatius conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, &amp; prudentius quia moderatius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath pleaſed His Majeſty by ſeveral Gratious Overtures to commend an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Proteſtant Subjects to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Parliament. A Deſign full of all Princely Wiſdom, Honeſty, and Goodneſs. In this Atchievement there is a double Intereſt (we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend) to be diſtinguiſh'd and weighed,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40985:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>that of <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf, and that of the <hi>Nation.</hi> The <hi>advance</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> does conſiſt much in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unity of its Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors both in Opinion and Practiſe to be of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and one, heart, and one Way (in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Worſhip) ſo far as may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Scriptures. The <hi>acknow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> doth lye in the Free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thing of Trade; and uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the whole Body in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pendance on the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. The one of theſe beſpeaks an <hi>eſtabliſh'd order and accommodation;</hi> the others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaks <hi>Indulgeare Liberty of Conſeience, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lleration:</hi> for while peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are in danger about Religion, we dare not launch out into Trade, (ſay they) but keep our Monnys, ſeeing we know not into what ſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghts we ſhall be driven, and when in reference to their party, they are held under ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie to thoſe who are deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ads, to mould thein into Wrath and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion: which without occaſion will melt and diſſolve it ſelf into bare
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40985:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>diffent of Opinion, peaceably rejoycing under the enjoyment of Profection.</p>
            <p>The King we know is concerned as Supream <hi>Governour,</hi> and as a <hi>Christian Protestant Governour.</hi> As he is <hi>King</hi> he is to ſeek the wellfare of the Nation; as he is a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> the flouriſhing of Religion, and the Proteſtan Religion particularly is his Intereſt, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom doth lye in Balance (he being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he chief Party) with its Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The Judgment now of ſome is for a <hi>comprehending Act.</hi> Which may take in thoſe who are for our Parochial Chaur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that ſeverity then might be uſed for reclaiming all whoſoever ſeparate from them: The Judgment of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is for a free and equal <hi>Act of Grace</hi> to all Indifferently, (the Papiſts with moſt excepted) whether ſeparaliſts or others) abhorring <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> as more dangerous to them on that account, mentioned, than all the Acts that have paſſed. Neither of theſe Judge up to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40985:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>the full Intereſt of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as is propoſed. It becomes not the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> if his Principles will admit him to own our Parochial Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and enjoy a Living to be willing to have his Brethren the <hi>Independants</hi> given up to perſecution: And it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes not the <hi>Sepanatiſis,</hi> if he may but enjoy his Conſcience, to repine or envy at the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> for reaping any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Emohiment, ſeeing both of them (ſuppoſing the latter may do ſo) have as much at bottom as can be, in their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, deſired of either. It is an Act therefore of a mixt Complexion, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding both <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> and <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> for the different Parties, muſt ſerve our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And to this end (as we may humbly hope) was there a Bill in the Houſe, <hi>A Bill for the eaſe of the Proteſtant Diſſenters in the Buſineſs of Religion.</hi> Which that it may (ſome time or other) be caſt into this model, we muſt preſent the ſame yet, under a little further Explication.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:40985:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>There are Two ſorts (we all know) of theſe Proteſtant Diſſentors: <hi>One</hi> that own the eſtabliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Miniſtry, and our Pariſh Congregations, and are in capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of union upon that account, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it heartily upon condeſcention to them in ſome ſmaller <hi>matters:</hi> The <hi>other</hi> that own nor our Churches, and ſo are uncapable of a Conjunction, who do not, and cannot deſue it, or ſeek it. For the <hi>one.</hi> That which we propoſe is a further latitude in the preſent conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted order, that ſuch may be received and this we call <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> or <hi>Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> Let us ſuppoſe that nothing elſe were required of a Man to be a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of a Pariſh, than there is to the Pariſhioner, to be a Member of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church, as part of the National. If a perſon Baptized will come to Church, and hear Common Prayer, and receive the Sacrament, and does nothing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Excommunication, he is, he may, he muſt be received for a Parochial Member: In like manner if a Miniſter
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40985:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>firſt ordained (and ſo <hi>Epiſcopally</hi> or <hi>Claſſically</hi> approved in his abilities for that function) will but read the Book of Liturgy, and adminiſter the Sacraments according to it, and does nothing which deſerves ſuſpenſion (we appeal to all indifferently ſober) why ſhould not this ſuffice a Man for the enjoying his Living, and exerciſing the Office unto which he is called) and what if ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e omiſſion here and there to ſalve a ſcrupulous Conſcience (ſo long as the main Body of the Service be ſtill read) were tollerated, would it do hurt to any?</p>
            <p>For the <hi>other,</hi> there is indeed nothing that can be done to bring thoſe in, and joyn them with us in Parochial union. Yet is there this to be propoſed, that you bear with them, and let not any be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted meerly for their Conſciences, and that we call <hi>Indulgence</hi> or <hi>Tolleration.</hi> If the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> now may be <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended,</hi> he will be ſatisfyed to act in his Miniſtry without endeavouring any <hi>Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40985:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>otherwiſe of <hi>Epiſcopacy:</hi> If the <hi>Congregationaliſt</hi> be <hi>indulged,</hi> he will be ſatisfied, though he be not <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended,</hi> for that he cannot ſubmit unto; and ſo ſhall there no diſ-obligation put on any, but all be pleaſed, and enjoy the <hi>eaſe</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Bill.</hi> Let but the Grounds of <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> be laid wide enough to take in all who can own and come unto the publick Liturgy, (the Conformiſt then we may ſuppoſe well the greater weight of the Nation) and when the Countenance of Authority, and all State Emoluments are caſt into one Scale, and others let alone to come on't, without perſecution to <hi>inflame</hi> them, or perferment to <hi>encourage</hi> them, (eſpecially if one Expedient be uſed which ſhall not paſs unmentioned in the cloſe, that ſuch as come in may find it really better to them to be a Prieſt to a Tribe, than a Levite to a Family) we need not doubt but Time, the Miſtreſs of the wiſe and unwiſe, will diſcover the peaceable Iſſue of ſuch Counſels.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:40985:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And here let us pauſe a little; for we imagine we ſee what <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies</hi> are hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> of the Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at this motion. What Prejudices and Impreſſions we mean have been laid on the Members by former A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Speech delivered by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> cellor in <hi>Chriſis-Church-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Parliament there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars aſſembled, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of contriving the <hi>Oxford Oath,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> quently of like former Impoſitions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt Magni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, as well a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y enough arroga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> It was, it ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of that Great Man, to root thoſe, Prime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ples out of Mens minds, upon which the late Wars (as he ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) were built; and he would do it by this Invention, <hi>to wit,</hi> the impoſing upon them new <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations. Oaths, Subſcriptions</hi> of a Strain framed contrary to choſe Principles. We do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emember now the Sentence of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras</hi> to the <hi>Apologue</hi> of the Angel, where the <hi>Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds</hi> and <hi>Seas</hi> would encounter
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40985:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>one another. <hi>Terily</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it was a fooliſh purpoſe:</hi> For the Trees could not come down from the Hills, nor the Waves get up from the Shoares. We muſt ſay the ſame of this Policy. It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a great vanity to think that Folks ſhould be made to ſwear away the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoughts and beliefs: Whatſoever it is we think or believe, we do think it, we do believe it, we muſt believe it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any of theſe outward Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. The Honeſt Man indeed will refuſe an Injunction againſt his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the Knave will ſwallow it, but each retain their <hi>Principles,</hi> which the laſt will be likelyeſt to put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>o any villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous <hi>practiſe.</hi> On the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rary there is nothing could be adviſed more certain, to keep the Covenant, and ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples alive in Mens Hearts and Memories, than this perpetual enjoying the <hi>Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> of it. Nor may you wonder, if that Leſſon ſink deep into Mans fleſh, which you will teach them with <hi>Briars</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> as <hi>Gideon taught the Men of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40985:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>Succoth.</hi> Beſides, it is the moſt unpoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick thing that ever could have been, for ſuch Contents as are of that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſequence to Majeſty, and the Government, to have them once diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or brought into queſtion, to be put into theſe <hi>Declarations, Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions,</hi> which neceſſitates the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of them to ſo many. It was the wiſdom of the antient Church inſtead of contention about the Jewiſh Ceremonies to take care they might have an Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Buriall: And we dare ſay, if that Great Lord Chancellour had but put off his Cap to the Covenant, and bidden it a fair adieu only, he ſhould have done more towards its Extirpation, than by all this iterated trouble to Mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. And if it ſhall therefore pleaſe the ſucceeding Miniſters of State inſtead of going to root out the Principles of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which are got into people, by this means (which is no means to do it, but the means to river them more into us) to endeavour rather to root out the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40985:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Cauſes</hi> from us, which make Men willing to entertain ſuch Principles, and deſire change: We ſuppoſe their Policy will prove the ſounder. The way to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the Throne of the King is this, to make it appear, that all thoſe <hi>Grievances,</hi> and all thoſe <hi>good things</hi> which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the late times expected to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved,</hi> or to be <hi>obtained</hi> by a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> or a change of the Government, may be more effectually accompliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by a King in the Acts of His Parliament.</p>
            <p>We are ſenſible how our Theam ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon us, and that we begin to ſhoot wide. We take our Aim there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore again, and Two things in earneſt we would expect from ſuch a <hi>Bill,</hi> as the ſum of what is neceſſary to the end of it, our <hi>eaſe,</hi> if it be made to ſerve the turn. The one is, that Biſhop <hi>Land</hi> be confined to his Cathedral; and the other, that Chancellor <hi>Hyde</hi> be totally expelled our Acts of Parliament. By the firſt we mean, that the Ceremonies in the ordinary Pariſh Churches be left to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40985:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>the liberty of the Miniſter, to uſe or uſe them not according to his Conſcience and Prudence towards his own Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: And by the <hi>latter</hi> that all theſe new deviſed <hi>Oaths, Subſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riptions</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations,</hi> together with the <hi>Canonical Oath,</hi> and <hi>the Subſcription in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> be ſuſpended for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e time to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. If that be too mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall content our ſelves with a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>r motion that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever theſe Declarations be that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be <hi>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ibed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> or <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orn.</hi> they may be impoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> only as to the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>end,</hi> leaving the taker but free to the uſe of their own <hi>Expreſſions.</hi> And this Expedient we gather from the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> who hath providently as it were againſt ſuch a ſeaſon laid in this Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>The form eſ the Subſcription ſet down in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nons, ratiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> by King</hi> James, <hi>was not expreſſed in the Act of the thirteenth of</hi> Elizabeth. <hi>Inſt. part.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 74. And conſequently, if the Clergy enjoyed this freedom until then, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Particular therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40985:39"/>what hinders why they might not have the ſame reſtored in reference alſo to others?</p>
            <p>It is true, that it may ſeem hard to many in the Parliament; to undo any thing themſelves have done: But though this be no <hi>rule</hi> for <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who are ſometimes to <hi>repent</hi> as well as to <hi>believe.</hi> If they be loath to <hi>Repeal</hi> any thing, what if they ſhall only <hi>interpret</hi> or <hi>explain.</hi> Let us ſuppoſe then ſome Clauſe in this <hi>Bill,</hi> or ſome new Act, for Explanations. If any Non-conformiſt cannot come up to the full meaning and intent of theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions rightly explained, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in <hi>Statu quo,</hi> under the ſtate only of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> without benefit of <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion;</hi> for ſo long as thoſe who are <hi>comprehended,</hi> may yet enjoy that <hi>Caſe</hi> as to be <hi>indulged</hi> in ſome equal meaſure anſwerable to His Majeſties late Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whether <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> be large or narrow, ſuch terms as we obtain are pure advantage, and ſuch as we obtain not, are no loſs. But if any does, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40985:40"/>can honeſtly agree to the whole ſenſe the Parliament intends in ſuch Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionr, why ſhould there be any obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for ſuch a Man, though he deliver himſelf in his own words, to be receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the eſtabliſh'd order with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, unleſs Men will look on theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions only to be continued for <hi>Engines of Battery</hi> to deſtroy the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts, and not as <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of unity to edifie the Church of God.</p>
            <p>We will not leave our <hi>Congregational</hi> Brethren neither, ſo long that we have ſomething more as may be ſaid for them, not ordinarily conſidered by any. It is this, That though indeed, they are not, and cannot ſeek to be of our Churches as they are <hi>Parochial</hi> under the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> or <hi>Super-intenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of the Biſhops: Yet do they not refuſe, but ſeek to be comprehended within the Church, as <hi>national</hi> under His Majeſty. We will explain our ſelves The Church may be conſidered as <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:40985:40"/>and ſo Chriſt alone is the Head of it, and we receive our Laws from him: Or as <hi>particular,</hi> and ſo the Paſtors are Heads, Guides, or Biſhops over their reſpective Flocks, who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded therefore <hi>to obey them in the Lord:</hi> Or as <hi>national,</hi> which is an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental and external reſpect to the Church of God, wherein the King is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Supream Head of it, and as we judge no otherwiſe; For thus alſo runs the Statute, <hi>That our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord ſhall be taken and reputed the only Supream Head in Farth of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>called</hi> Eccleſia An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicana. Now if it ſhould pleaſe the King and Parliament to allow and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe <hi>ſeparate Meetings,</hi> and <hi>ſtated places for Worſhip</hi> by a Law, as His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty did by His Declaration, we muſt Profeſs that, as ſuch Aſſemblies by this means muſt be conſtituted immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egral parts</hi> of the Church as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, no leſs than our Pariſh Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations: So would the Congregate
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40985:41"/>Churches (at leaſt thoſe that underſtand themſelves) own the King for Head over them, in the ſame ſence as we own him Head over ours, that is as much as to ſay, for the Supreme <hi>Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive</hi> Governour of all, (in this acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal regard) both to keep every ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Congregation to that Goſpel-order themſelves profeſs; and to ſuperviſe their Conſtitutions in things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that nothing be done but in ſubordination to the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>Well, let us ſuppoſe then a liberty for theſe ſeparate Aſſemblies under the viſitation of His Majeſty and His Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, and not the Biſhops: We would fain know what were the evil you can find in them. If it lie in any thing, it muſt be in that you call Schiſme. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration then let us know in it ſelf ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply conſidered is nothing, neither good nor evil. There may be reaſon to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide</hi> or <hi>ſeparate</hi> ſome Chriſtians from others out of prudence, as the <hi>Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:40985:41"/>of old from the <hi>fully inſtructed,</hi> for their greater edification; and as a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel or two is added to a Pariſh Church, when the people elſe were too big a Congregation. It is not all <hi>diviſion</hi> then or <hi>ſeparation</hi> is Schiſme, but <hi>ſinful divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Now the Supream Authority as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Head having appointed the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Meetings, and required all the Subjects of the Land to frequent them, and them alone, for the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, glorifying, or national ſerving and worſhiping the one only True God, and His Son, whom we have generally received, and this Worſhip or Service in the nature of it being intrinſically good, and the External order (ſuch as that of time and place, and the like Circumſtances) being properly under his Jurisdiction, it hath ſeemed to us hitherto, that unleſs there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in that order and way preſcribed, which is ſinful, and that required too as a condition of that Communion, there is no man could refuſe his atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40985:42"/>on theſe Parochial Aſſemblies, without the ſin of diſobedience: And conſequently his ſeparation thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming ſinful, proves Schiſm: But if the Scene be alter'd, and thoſe ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Aſſemblies made legal; the Schiſm in reference to the national upon the ſame account does vaniſh. Schiſm is a ſeparation from that Church, whereof we <hi>ought,</hi> or are <hi>bound</hi> to be Members: If the Supream Authority then looſe our obligation to the Pariſh Meeting, ſo that we are bound no longer, the <hi>iniquity,</hi> (we ſay upon this account) <hi>is not to be found,</hi> and the Schiſm gone. Loe here, a way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (if they pleaſe) to rid the trouble and ſcruple of Schiſm (at once) out of the Land. If they pleaſe not, yet is there ſomething to be thought on for the Separatiſt in a way of <hi>forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> that the innocent Chriſtian, at leaſt, as it was in the time of <hi>Trajan,</hi> may not be <hi>ſought out unto puniſhment.</hi> Eſpecially when ſuch a Tolleration only
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40985:42"/>is deſired, as is conſiſtant with the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith,</hi> a <hi>good life,</hi> and <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſay then to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, which is the Objection hit ſtill in their Teeth that plead for moderation? Why, we will not baulk the delivery of our opinion. There are Two parts we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs of that favour or condeſcenſion we ſeek from the Higher Powers: The one conſiſting of a <hi>Compoſition</hi> with thoſe whoſe Principles are fit and capable of it: And the other conſiſting of <hi>forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> towards thoſe whoſe Principles will allow them no more. The Papiſt in our account is but one ſort of Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, and the conſcientions and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able among them muſt be held in the ſame Predicament with thoſe among our ſelves, that likewiſe refuſe to come to Common Prayer. It is true, we have Laws very ſevere againſt the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, and Seminary Prieſt: But this we ſuppoſe to be upon the ground of State Intereſt. The Supremacy of the Pope,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40985:43"/>and the Authority of the King are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent in this Land: The Prieſt and Jeſuite are taken by Law as Factors for the Pope; and an undermining the Government in all States is a Capital Crime. But as for the common Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, who lives innocently in his way, he is to us as other Separatiſts, and ſo comes under the like Tolleration. That is, he is not to expect to have power or truſt, being not of the Religion of the State; but he may hope for the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Conſcience <hi>as we,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wrong or oppreſſion. And indeed if it be only Liberty of Conſcience that he ſeeks, this will be ſufficient, that he is not troubled, <hi>nor we.</hi> If he deſires more, he ſtirs us all preſently into Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and no wonder if we be very ſollicitous to have Popery kept out of <hi>Dominion,</hi> or our ſelves from Fire and Faggot, how gentle and equal ſoever we be to it, and to all parties alike un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſafe <hi>Subjugation.</hi> For as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick we ſuppoſe will conſider
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40985:43"/>that to go to bring in a Religion upon a people that are no more prepared for theirs then we are in this Nation, were the committing of a Rape upon the publick Conſcience, and poſſeſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got without our good wills would not likly be long retained: So are we to remember the common rule of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity towards them, and to all Men, that we muſt do as we would be done by, and that, <hi>with what meaſure we mete to others, if ſhall be met to us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we turn us to the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. My Lords and Gentlemen! We ſuppoſe you honeſt Perſons that would not depart from this Catholick Rule, that would not wrong any, and if you did, would make them recompence. There have been very hard Acts paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which when the Bills were brought in, might haply look ſmooth, and fair to you: But you ſaw not the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Art, ſecret Machination, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely contrived Snares againſt one
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40985:44"/>whole Party. If ſuch a form of words would not, another ſhould do their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs: By this means, you in the firſt place your ſelves, ſome of you were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſtript: Multitudes diſpoſſeſs'd of their Livings: The Vineyard let out to others: The Lord Jeſus the Maſter of it deprived of many of His Faithful La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers: And the Poor Sheep (what had they done?) bereft of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Spiritual Food, to the hazard of their Eternal Souls. Among many Arguments therefore for Liberty in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Papers, from <hi>Policy, Convenience, Reaſon of State,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon of Religion,</hi> we have this one to offer you of a more binding Nature, an Argument from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Reſtitution</hi> to the wronged. It is true, that the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they once had, are filled and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of: But there are others enough. There are many of thoſe who poſſeſs <hi>theirs,</hi> do alſo keep their <hi>own,</hi> and keep more. There are many who are <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Deans, Prebendaries,</hi> that are alſo
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40985:44"/>
               <hi>Parſons, Rectors, Vicars:</hi> Who have Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices and Honours by Heaps, and by the Buſhel. If it ſhall pleaſe you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this <hi>Bill</hi> on the Anvil, or in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take Cognizance of <hi>Pluraliſts,</hi> that for the preventing an idle, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, covetouſly overgrown, unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Miniſtry, every Man who hath more than one <hi>cure of Souls,</hi> or one dignity, ſhall give them up into a Publick ſtock, or to a general diſtribution, you ſhall do the Church right, and the Eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted right, you ſhall give ſuch Drones their due, and God His due, and ſtrew the way by this means, for making your Grace intended in this Bill, of ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification. In the Name of God Sirs, let us move you to this; if it were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>hae vice,</hi> for a preſent needful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of us at this ſeaſon. We ſee the Jaws of the Jeſuite, and the Sectary opening upon us; If the ſober Proteſtant Intereſt be not united, we periſh. We know who will be ready to ſtamp here, and throw duſt in the Air; for it is theſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40985:45"/>
               <hi>Sons of the Horſleech,</hi> whoſe Voice is <hi>give, give,</hi> that will never be contented with a <hi>ſingle Portion.</hi> A <hi>Dignity</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a <hi>Living,</hi> let them be allowed: But one <hi>Dignity,</hi> and one <hi>cure of Souls.</hi> it is therefore this hard Objection at the bottom, the Prieſts covetouſneſs, and corruption, rather than their diſpute about this indifferent, that really hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Churches Peace and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity.</p>
            <p>We ſhall therefore for the gentle en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of this, humbly offer you ſome Reaſons.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt, that Pluraliſts were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the Church at firſt upon the account only of neceſſity; becauſe they had not Miniſters enough that could Preach to the People. They could get ſome to <hi>Read,</hi> but none to give them a <hi>Sermon:</hi> And upon this account, they admitted one to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor to ſeveral Congregations. But now the Land does abound with ſo many Miniſters, who have <hi>never a cure,</hi> and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40985:45"/>ſuch as are no leſs learned, and more painful in Preaching, than thoſe that have <hi>three or four.</hi> We will plead with theſe Men before Heaven, and before you who are the Heads of our Tribes aſſembled, that it is not pious, not fit, nor political, (that is not for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good) that this Cuſtom ſhould continue, when the Reaſon is ceaſed; eſpecially when ſo many of thoſe that are put out have Families, and ſcarce Bread to ſubſiſt.</p>
            <p>It is a ſaying ſince the times of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> That when the Church had but <hi>Wooden Chalices,</hi> it had <hi>Golden Prieſts;</hi> but when they had <hi>Golden Chalices,</hi> and rich Benefices, they had <hi>Wooden Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi> That Religion brought forth Riches, and the Daughter hath devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Mother. It is pity that Men who are called to this Function, which requires them to be Examples to others of humility, lowlineſs of mind, ſelf-denal, and mortification, ſhould be lead ſo much as they are into the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40985:46"/>idleneſs, and exceſs by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments. For as it hath been reflected upon by ſome of the Houſe; and other Gentlemen who ſerved the King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repairs, as an errour of the State in the late Reſtauration of Epiſcopacy, that the profits of the Church-Lands for twenty years together ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed at once on a few ſingle perſons, which would have leiſurely requited a great many: So are they really as little pleaſed to have the Prieſt, who was perhaps a while ago, their Servitor at the Univerſity, or Tenants Son, or ſomething meaner than they will ſay, ſhould by the ſudden accumulation of ſo many places as he hath had Simonical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or Gratuitouſly conferred upon him, be huffed up to that pompous height and vanity, of his Coach and Liveries, as makes him to become the very envy of of his Patron, and ſcandal to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>It is true, that the Nobility Spiritual and Temporal have the Prerogative to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40985:46"/>capacitate a Miniſter according to Law for divers Livings: But when Jeſus Chriſt the great Maſter of the Vineyard does command their labour, and that they <hi>feed the Flock over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made them Overſeers,</hi> there is no ſuch priviledge to be urged, but in the nature of the thing it is void. There there is no Cuſtom, no Right, no Law, if the King, Lords, and Commons, if the whole World ſhould agree to make it, that can be of force againſt the Goſpel. <hi>Nulla datur poteſtas ad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are few of you who are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in either Houſes without jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that the <hi>Romanists</hi> were borrowing an <hi>Helve</hi> for their <hi>Hatchet</hi> out of the <hi>Wood</hi> of the Fanaticks; and that if they came to obtain their purpoſe: It is not hard to conjecture, which <hi>Trees</hi> were like to go down, one after another. As thoſe Men of the Church therefore are ſo willing you ſhould do ſomething for the ſecurity of your Religion and them,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40985:47"/>it is meet that they ſhould be ready to contribute to it. That they who preach the Goſpel to others, ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to put the great duty of it, which is <hi>ſelf-abrenuntiation</hi> into pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe themſelves. For that Man is not ſit to be a Miniſter of Chriſt, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into His Vineyard at all, that does not look more to his <hi>Word,</hi> than to his <hi>Penny,</hi> and ſeeks not the wellfare of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above his advancement; and had not rather convert <hi>one Soul,</hi> than get <hi>two Livings,</hi> and have a <hi>Prebend</hi> to ſpare. According to what every Mans mind is moſt upon in his Sphear (the <hi>publick,</hi> Intereſt, or his <hi>own</hi>) ſuch is his value more or leſs.</p>
            <p>However this be, whether they are willing or not, there is an univerſal <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens dominium</hi> in the Supream legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Authority that puts an end to all Cavil (if there ariſe any) <hi>de jure privatorum:</hi> And we will conclude with this, that whatſoever things, are therefore ſubſtantially profitable for
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40985:47"/>the Community, and are retarded only by the intereſt of private perſons, theſe are things moſt truly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the Conſultation of Parliament. God Almighty keep alive the true <hi>Engliſh,</hi> publick Spirit. God preſerve the Proteſtant Religion, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the King. God proſper an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We of the Kings Party</hi> (ſays Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi>) <hi>did, and do deteſt all Grievances of the People, as much as any Men living.</hi> In his <hi>Lex Terrae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a certain Truth, This King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom without an Act of Oblivion, and a meet regard had to tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, will unavoidably be ruined.</hi> In the Armies Indempnity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſay again, That without a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious general Pardon from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, and a favourable regard had to tender Conſciences, there will be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Truth nor Peace in the Land, nor
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40985:48"/>any Man ſecure of any thing that he hath.</hi> In his Cordial for the good People of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again in His Declaration for Tryals of Treaſons, and all Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Crimes to be by a Jury, <hi>They that love this Common-wealth, will uſe all means to procure an Act of Oblivion, and tender Conſciences a just and reaſonable ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, elſe we muſt all periſh firſt or laſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40985:48"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40985:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
